topic today's topic is about uh the
hidden marov model we finally uh dive
into the uh the uh the formulation of
the hdu marok model
problem so today's agenda is uh
the we actually try to formulate the hmm
hidden Mark model based on the EM
algorithm to do that we actually need to
kind of a uh
the perform the four step for this the
formulation so I actually try to explain
this for formul four step for the hmm
formulation and then we move to the
weekly
assignment so by the way uh this lecture
is again uh
quite diving to the formulation part and
someone may think that you know first
you know hmm is already the classical
method so it may not be very important
for the end to as so partly yes if you
guys are only using the attention based
method but as we discuss in the CTC and
RN transmisser the hard alignment
problem actually still exist in our the
latest speech technology and currently
this is actually the the one of the
standard technique so instead of just
the skipping this part we are actually
the focusing on the formulation
part and another discussion would be
that do we need a formulation we don't
need a formulation it's already you know
someone that solved it 30 years ago and
already have an algorithm right we just
implement it which is also one
option uh but in this other lecture I
try to kind of also for you guys to
understand the
formulation this is based on my EXP
if we try to do the research or if we
try to make a kind of new
technology uh we actually need to build
a new
algorithm in this case we actually have
to the formulate the problem by
ourselves so I'm I want you guys not
just kind of you know the making speech
recogition to be uh using the speech
Technologies but I also want you guys to
you know build or make new speech
algorithm so this is why I kind of try
to spend the time to uh how to formulate
a problem and so on and I'm very sure
that again CMU from CMU many of the
technique came out and many of the new
algorithm came out from CMU from you
guys you know the higher generation of
the you guys always created a state of
the
techniques so I really want you guys to
be one of them so that's why I kind of
focus on the the formulation part little
bit but later after of course of course
the formulation we have solved the
equation to do the kind of algorithm
part and then implementation part is
mostly using the this kind of following
the algorithm but let's also try to
understand this formulation
part okay so the now that I move to the
the the speech condition the acoustic
modeling part which is mainly using the
hmm so which is under focusing of p o
given L right which I have kind of
explained many times and I also want to
kind of recap the three the
equations had some kind of a similarity
here right by the way the last time
mentioned that this equation skipping
the several condition Independence
assumption you are right actually I
found that there are lot of condition
independent assump I kind of ignored so
I kind of corrected this one and the
previous slide as well
but anyway the the last time we
discussed that every time we started
from PW given all and then formulating
this problem right and this actually PW
given o is also becomes a kind of
important uh our the objective
function so uh with this kind of a the
objective function soal
likelihood we try to find the parameters
that maximizing this parameter so uh
from now on I actually didn't kind of
include the model parameter but from now
on I actually including the model
parameter here and then try to kind of
estimate
it by using the maximum likelihood
basically you know uh the the criteria
is the this one you know starting from
this one and try to kind of find the uh
uh the most likely uh parameter uh based
on the kind of whatever like the EM
algorithm or back propagation or
whatever but this lecture we will use
the EM algorithm to explain it and
another important note is that the yes
uh we will focus on the acoustic
modeling part P or given
L but every time if we have a kind of a
the the condition L that is kind of that
we have too many uh the the uh uh the
two redundant equations so just in this
lecture we omit the kind of the
condition of the the L the P sequ but
this is just for the Simplicity we omit
it always you remember that this kind of
hmm equation is given the kind of foring
sequences right but just omit it uh to
for the Simplicity of the uh the
equation and so
on okay and then we will kind of discuss
about the the four step uh to the
formulate this hm problem with the EM
algorithm so one other the step is
Introduction of the latent variable
second step is two other make a complete
data likelihood function and the third
step is orary function
and the fourth fourth step is the
parameter estimation and I will explain
uh this kind of are the uh the each of
the kind of a step the one by
one but before moving to that that I
just want to mention why uh we use the
uh the EM algorithm maximum likely with
em algorithm uh instead of the back
propagation uh or other kind of
estimation method uh in this
lecture so first the EM algorithm is
quite the powerful when we kind of
introducing the latent variable and
using this kind of
the the the auxiliary function form so
em algorithm is actually with the normal
the estimation process this kind of of
the likelihood based part is very
difficult but instead we actually try to
kind of introduce the latent variable
and then using this uh the auxiliary
function uh instead of likelihood
function to estimate this uh the uh the
the parameter so this is a kind of the
high level explanation about the EM
algorithm so and then why instead of
using this kind of other
function we using this kind of a
complicated form is that based on the
kind of the the the the inequality uh
the the relationship I will skip the
detail of this inequality the
explanation but always uh this the
likelihood function and auxilary
function has a this kind of a
relationship and then if the the
auxilary function
the parameter is updated always it's
corresponding to increasing the max
likelihood function so by using this
kind of indirect way we always assure
that this uh method actually find the
local Optimum the
likelihood the the values the based on
this the EM algorithm so the initially
the people started to use the EM
algorithm
instead of the back
propagation and the EM algorithm has
actually lot of pros and
cons so first uh it is uh very
beautifully
monotonic so uh the if for example uh
the if you monitor the your em algorithm
and the likelihood value is
decrease I'm very sure that it has a bug
in your uh implement
because em algorithm always this
step increase the
lik thetically it is actually uh the the
uh the proed so this property is
actually very good property when we make
a kind of a system uh and so on it's
quite easy to debar and quite easy to
kind of find the the the how much our
kind of model is improved as kind of
iteration
goes I think many people here may have
an experience of the back propagation
with the neur network right this is not
like this right if you guys did some
wrong hyper parameter or too many kind
of iterations it's sted to kind of
decrease the performance right so em
algor we don't have such or if that
happen again the your implementation may
be
wrong it is quite easy to devel and when
we don't have so much kind of the
computational power and so one uh this
kind of property was very very important
so that the people started to use the EM
algorithm uh this approach is uh the
also the uh depend on the initialization
this is actually similar to the uh the
uh back propagation right and then the
uh other kind of a one of the big
drawback of the EM algorithm is that
it's cannot be uh the the uh the go to
the global Optimum in many cases it just
stuck to the local Optimum
easily so if for example we set a WR
initialization and the local Optimum is
nearby and then the EM algorithm is just
stucking to there and then there's no
way to actually uh the the escape from
the uh the the this kind of local optim
which is again different from back
propagation back propagation we could
fortunately luckily with running
parameters or B size we can actually
escape from the local Optimum
but we canot so the only way to avoid a
local Optimum is to find the better
initialization and another nice part of
the EM algorithm is easy to the
distribute even uh the the especially I
will explain it later but Eep part is
fully parallelized so we could actually
easily using the the hundred thousand of
CPUs or gpus very easily and then
basically the performance may not be so
much changed just a numerical uh the the
the uh the the difference can happen uh
so that is a kind of nice property and
uh well there are some but the property
as well of the the EM algorithm so
initially people actually starting to
use this kind of property and then uh
the making a
speech okay so I will explain about this
kind of a four step and always please
remember this by the for step uh there
are several other application that we
can use for the EM the algorithm like
gaussia mixture modeling and so on by
the way K means a kind of a one the
extreme case of the the gaan mixture
model and the K's algorithm can also be
interpreted as an em algorithm and GMM
may not be so used anymore but k mean we
still use it uh in the especially in the
the sell superv running so it's good to
remember em algorithm anyway and this is
based on this kind four uh Thea step
okay first starting from the
introduction of the latent
variable so this what is latent variable
it actually can be anything but this is
basically unobservable value that we
want to kind of introduce and then that
we want to use this kind of latent
variable to actually support to Sol our
problem and then uh the for speech uh
the recognition problem we actually have
a very good relat variable candidate
which is alignment
variable so as this know that as we
mentioned you know if we know the
alignment problem our problem is
actually quite kind of easily tractable
right but alignment itself is not
observable so we have to consider it as
a kind of probabilistic variable so in
the hmm we actually using this alignment
variable as a probabilistic variable
latent variable variable is in the word
in the EM algorithm the context and then
actually in speech processing in speech
problem alignment variable becomes L
variable okay so one one part
is easily kind of the fixed what kind of
in the latent variable we should
introduce for speech cases we just using
the this alignment variable that we have
discussed
before okay by the way uh the one kind
of a important remark which I kind of
mentioned many times how to introduce a
new variable in the probabilistic
formulation yes yes thank you so
much now you guys remember it right so
it was used for when we kind of are
introducing the pH sequence and now it
is also using in the uh the introducing
the rat variable alignment variable and
so on and again please note that they
always you know in our cases that the
the uh The Forum sequence is given but
we just kind of omit it for the
Simplicity of the explanation and so
on okay uh move to the next part uh next
let's try to uh the uh make a complete
data likelihood
function and I will explain that what is
complete data
likely so in the EM algorithm uh context
we can actually consider the latent
variable if lat variable is observed the
problem can be actually completely
observed so we could actually solve the
problem easily so in this case for
example the O and S both are kind of
observation and they are it's in the
kind of argument cases this is called
complete data uh the
and the complete data
likely and the in the mathematically we
actually introduce complete data you
know by using this kind of sum rule
right and this other form is other
complete data uh likelihood but
actually it is not the end this
observation is you know the sequence uh
the alignment variable rat variable is
sequence so this joint Pro ility is
actually quite difficult to deal with so
then we actually are using the
factorization and conditional
Independence assumption which we also
use a little bit in the CTC or RN
transmissor the formulation but we let's
try to do that again in the this hmm
cases and this one is actually not uh so
uh the simple
uh the we first using the uh product
rule uh or uh that we could say that the
generalized version of the product rule
called The Chain rule to actually uh the
convert each of the observation to this
kind of form of the uh the uh equation I
hope everyone can understand this just
you know we have a two variable joint
variable gathering together but other
than that this is a kind of a just
simple the chain from one and T and T
one to T minus one so if we for example
you guys just to kind of remove the one
of the variable it would be very
familiar a chain rule for you but just
have a kind of two variabl that's it and
this is just the product rule chain
Rule and then uh we also try to
factorize this kind of a two a
distribution from here to here maybe not
so difficult for everyone right just you
know using the product rule and from
here to here since we have a many kind
of a conditions so it looks bit bit
complicated but this is also just kind
of using the uh the product rule and
then keeping OT and St and the St here
becomes a condition and so on so this
also a lot of kind of condition I
apologize for that but it is a nature of
this kind of problem and but this is
also still kind of
product and then uh from here to here we
actually performing a conditional
Independence assumption and this is
again you know it is not kind of a the
the some kind of a theory or whatever
we're just assuming that these are not
independent with
others and again this is a limitation of
the hmm uh some of the Assumption is too
big right for example from here to here
observation is independent of the the
previous observation which is a little
bit too much right uh and the this the
alignment to get the alignment all the
entire kind of previous observation and
the uh the all the kind of State until T
minus 2 are not dependent it is you know
not the the the reasonable assumption
but this is a way to actually solving uh
this kind of a problem so by doing that
we could actually the the mathematically
solve this uh the problem so this is
again uh this is the
Assumption and then finally uh May
taking the uh the the the this kind of
form of the uh the the
equation so first one is uh the the
observation one which is only depending
on the uh the alignment State s and then
this also has a kind of Prior
distribution of s and this is a kind of
time step one from the time step two we
similarly uh the observation is only
depending on the uh the alignment SD but
this alignment SD is depending on the
previous
alignment and this is actually the hmm
the one of the the critical uh the the
Assumption uh so the with this kind of
hm structure we can actually derive uh
this kind of a the probabilistic uh the
equation uh and so on
so from here to here uh quite simplified
right so now you know the we can
actually the three factorize the kind of
the each of the the function Pro
function over the time so it can be a
kind of a good to tackle this kind of
problem
however what is this observation you
know given the state to generating the
observation
uh just a kind of a probability of the
State uh we actually have to providing
the actual form of the the distributions
for this kind of
programs uh by the way that will be
explained later but this is actually
final form over the hmm so the the the
lecture three we we discussed this one
right and the uh and the previous kind
of a discussion we introduced the
alignment right and then the previous
slide we further factorized this one
right so this is a kind of a final form
of the the speech equation solved by the
uh the hmm uh based
approaches uh so this are the the the
from here to uh derive here again note
that we don't use the uh the any of the
kind of approximation except for the
conditional Independence assumption
product rule and the sum
rule uh by the way in my laboratory uh
we usually ask the student to derive
from here to
here without checking anything so this
is actually practice we we ask the
student to do that uh I think you guys
had hard time right so we will have this
kind of exercise
later okay
um okay so uh the this is a kind of a uh
the the distribution uh the but the
again this is not still the actual
distribution right so from now on I kind
of providing the uh the what kind of a
distribution uh the concrete form of the
distribution uh we should provide and
there is two option by the way one is to
uh the use the kind of a the appropriate
distribution uh the which I will explain
later but the other way is is just using
it this function the represented by the
neural network so this approach uh is
called hybrid hmm deep neuron Network
the method because this kind of
formulation itself is the quite kind of
hm based approaches but each of the kind
of distribution is replaced by the Deep
neural network so this actually approach
called hybrid hm DNN is actually one of
the standard method in our the speech
equ but again now it it is kind of
gradually replaced by the N2 and S and
then that will also be covered in our
lecture but today uh let's try to kind
of use the another kind of way which is
you know setting the appropriate
distribution with the tractable concrete
form of the distribution and then the
Sol with in the EM
algorithm okay so uh the first the let's
focus on this the distribution
PST given St minus one and S S one which
appeared here and here
right and this one is usually uh we just
using the multinomial uh distribution
which is kind of a the the standard
distribution of forming the discrete the
category from one to J to kind of a
showing some kind of weight and so on
this kind of a the the problem is
usually the the set by the maromi
distribution and the nice part of the
marial distribution is that this kind of
parameter wants to have a kind of
constraint like always it have to be the
the the positive and it's other have to
be kind of sum to one but momal
distribution is satisfying this kind of
a condition so that for this the PST
given minus one and S1 uh we are usually
using the uh the momal
distribution and the next
one observation T are given the St the
Ceta and this one is actually the
observation is M or whatever which is a
continuous
Vector okay previous one is actually
using it as a kind of a discrete
category and making it as a weight but
now it becomes the continuous dist the
the values and in this case we actually
using the gaussian gaussian distribution
where gaussian usually have our
parameters in the mean and the Coan
Matrix and so on by the way this
distribution is also called emission
probability because it emit the
observation and then there the one kind
of discussion is H why we use
cauan we could actually using dat
distribution right we can use a GMA
distribution we can also use a student
distribution we can use a r
distribution the RAS distribution there
will be many kind of
possible options to set the distribution
it's in
based on the kind of how to say the
short stale property it's easy to kind
of the uh the and represented as the
exponential right and then it is easy to
actually uh the model the the gaussian
correct this kind of property is called
exponential family distribution and this
is actually one of the requirement but
by the way exponential distribution we
still have other options like a gamma
distri distribution and so on I don't
know how many people know gamma
distribution but the gamma distribution
can also be an option but we don't use a
gamma distribution because gamma
distribution usually kind of the limit
the domain only with the
positive but the gaussian distribution
is actually the uh domain is not bounded
minus infinity to Infinity So This is
speech feature after taking a log it's
actually can be kind of a followed by
this kind of a domain so the domain is
also another important information if we
set a kind of correct the distribution
and so on so again uh the power Spectrum
for example uh still may be good to use
gaussian because it's easy to use but as
a kind of byon the domain probably
better to uh the model Go Gamma
distribution
that the naturally
satisfy the non- negative
constraint um but anyway there's some
kind of the uh the knowledge what kind
of distribution we should set for the
kind of each of the distribution and so
on but anyway luckily we have a gaussian
which is a kind of a very useful
function to mostly kind of cover many of
the the problem and so on and I kind of
writing the two kind of the the gaussian
distribution one is that probably the
this is the kind of most people know
this one right just normal the Coan
Matrix but in the I think some of you
here may you know take the machine
learning courses and they may know that
uh Coan Matrix is actually very
difficult to estimate or very difficult
to deal with computational cost is very
large so instead in our machine learning
problem we quite often use the co
diagonal
coant this is mean that there's no kind
of the uh the uh the the zero in the of
diagonal element and only non zero are
the value in the diagonal element and it
also should be positive uh uh this are
the the uh the uh type of the gaan is
called the Gan distribution with the
diagonal coas in my lecture and this is
actually quite easy once it is diagonal
even by the way we can factorize it with
each of the dimension because we don't
care about the the correlation and so on
so the the uh equation is farther simple
it's just a kind of a multiplication of
the scalar single gaan distribution and
so on
and then uh let's uh discuss about the
diagonal Coan versus gr Coan so diagonal
Coan since it is you know the diagonal
element is zero so it's actually have a
limitation of the covering the kind of a
information like for example diagonal
and the F the most diff different part
is that H can actually change the kind
of a
tilting so this kind of Freedom this is
only the the degree of freedom in only
kind of a two dimensional case just one
but if it is actually the many
dimensions this kind of flexibility is
very kind of cool however this actually
the increase number of parameters are
lot and the computational parameters are
lot so that is a kind of a issue if we
try to deal with a huge number of the
the data in our
cases uh like for example this is actual
uh the distribution of the MCC but the
to make it kind of easily visualize I
only extract one and two Dimension it's
the original one is the the mod the 10
Dimension uh and the single gaan to try
to fit it um I think it's not very well
fit right and uh
karian that since we can make King it so
it's actually not very
bad but uh in the actual kind of a
problem we often using the multiple
gaussian but diagonal
Coan this is actually way to kind of
efficiently modeling our data pattern
and so on so not only for speech many of
the engineering problem we of using the
multiple gaan with dyam uh d Al Coan
again F Coan can be more accurate but it
has many parameters and it's difficult
to deal with so this is quite often the
people are using it and this kind of
multiple Gan based the the distribution
is called the the the gaussian mixture
gaan mixture model and so on the gaan
mixture model has additional parameter
which is the number of gaan in this case
is k equal four
and then uh the this the weight is also
kind of a satisfying with the z0 to one
and the some to1 condition so it is
normally actually represented by the
maral momal distribution and so on but
anyway again the in our engineering
problem we often using gaan mixture but
we often use the diagonal Coan okay but
in the
following uh the for formulation gaan Mi
is a little bit complicated so as you
see we already have a lot of variable in
the formulation right so I kind of omit
the gaan mixture and then a single
gaussian and then continue the kind of
formulation uh but later I will extend
it to the gaan mixture model and
practically we using a gaan mixture
model but from the following the in the
formulation I use a single gaan
distribution
okay so uh yeah this a kind of summary
that now you know this kind of equations
is replaced by the gaussian distribution
and the the some kind of weight
parameter which is also we can call it
maomi distribution so now these are the
equations are actually distributed uh so
represented of the concrete form of the
distribution
ever uh we didn't talk about you know
how to estimate uh these parameters
right mean uh diagonal variance and this
weight parameters and so on so this is
the target of this lecture hope it will
be finished in this uh if not I will
continue in the next
week okay uh to solve this one this uh
actually problem uh estimation problem
is not very easy
and we actually as I mentioned we have
to use the EM algorithm and to use the
EM algorithm we use the auxiliary
function that I defined
before and the first part is I just kind
of write the definition of the auxiliary
function here listed in the my kind of
the previous note in the
lecture introducing the uh the lat
variable and so on and look at this one
p given s
CA this is the the the distribution that
we deal deal with in the previous step
right now we kind of know the way to uh
the represent this one with a gaussian
distribution and M distribution here
apologize it is very small but if you go
to the previous slide you guys can check
the detailed one right so how to the the
the further formulate this one of course
we can just substitute this one to this
p uh s given CA right so let's do that
and then uh we actually can uh the
decompose this uh the distribution to
the three
component one is the the the initial
weight the other is the transition
weight and the third part is Gan so this
the equation change is not very this
part just using the uh just changing the
uh the since it is product here right
and the product inside the log means
that it become the summation right it's
just kind of you know split to the each
time that's it I didn't do
anything okay and actually this each of
the term is very difficult to uh solve
in general I will mention the reason
this is because we have a summation over
sequence so we couldn't basically solve
this one so but fortunately this form is
actually having a solution so mirac we
have a solution so I will show you that
so to do that we actually using the
three kind of technique one is the
sequence DEC composition the other is
the distributor property and the third
one is the
our kind of open use Su Rule and these
three are just kind of you know
rewriting the equation it's not like
doing some kind of rule and so on and I
will explain it one by one so first part
sequence DEC
composition so anyway sequence is a kind
of an issue because it is you know the
very kind of complicated right and it's
you know like one to T and in our case
it's alignment right and this uh the
again just the dealing with the sequ is
always difficult
challenging but the the for example one
of the equation here is actually
extracted from the the previous slide uh
the uh this part or the other part in
this other part so anyway uh the in this
example uh this part is only depending
on the
S1 right and in this part only this part
is depending on the S minus one to
St uh among all kind of sequence only
kind of depending on the S1 or only
depending on two kind of variable so in
this cases for the kind of later the the
factorization it is better to kind of
split the SE to like a S1 and s22 to T
or the
S1 this one S1 to T minus 2 just
subsequence and then s minus one s t and
then T +1 to tence I don't do anything
but I just
kind this sequence okay I think I people
understand yeah just but this is
important okay otherwise SE is directly
dealing with the sequence is very
difficult so just the using this trick
to reite the
sequence and then after uh rewriting the
sequence that becomes actually this F
equation I didn't do anything but it's
just rewriting S1 to and S2 to P by the
way we start corresponding summation is
also I just
these are kind of first trick and the
second part is a distributed property
these actually very cool I think
everyone knows but for this kind of
problem very cool so I want to spend the
that some time so anyway uh the other
kind of a problem is that the summation
over the sequence which is almost
impossible for us to solve so like for
example uh just a one
example let's say this kind of s is you
know we only consider the three
state and the SE length is about 200 and
if this is 10 millisecond it's only 2
second only two second and three kind of
the state of the
sequence the the actually the number of
seant would be many quite large can
compute it
um three to the power of 200
right we cannot use it in the computer
right only three
category and then only two second of the
uh the uh the the speech
sample we cannot actually deal with all
possible
elment so
uh the basically if the this summation
over the sequence appears we have to try
to avoid this one and then one of the
kind of a cool direction to solve this
one is that distributed
property and the distributed property is
the very simple and I believe everyone
know it right
uh here one example right
we can compute ax plus a
y but this is you know factorize with a
and then we actually can reduce the
computational cost
right and this is super simple example
but the the more little bit complicated
a FN and summation no n one way is you
know directly Computing this one but
since a is not depend depending on the
end so we can actually factorize it and
then we only compute this one we don't
have to compute the eight times FN every
time right the number of multiplication
is are quite largely R and a bit more
kind of the general form but still this
is true we have a two function and and
and GM and summation over n and
M so this one is also looks very
complicated but it's actually can
factorize it and then take the summation
for each of them and we actually can
reduce the computational cost right I
just write the kind of sh code so if
there's no distributed property in the
world and then we actually have to
compute this kind of a double Loop n
m but by using the distributed property
we can actually you know the Performing
the summation once twice and only how
about other the uh the the computation
cost of is the n plus M and so on right
so this actually the property is used in
our uh the the summation the the problem
and then the making this the previous
equation could be somehow
trable so this is actually the the this
part so from here to
here as you can see that this one is
only depending on the S1 right not
depending on the s2t right so we can
actually change the kind of a uh this
part to be inserted here and factorizing
this part
okay very cool right uh but this part
the the sequence de composition just
reting the uh the uh the the sequence
and the distributed property they just
kind of know changing the kind of a
order right although this is very
important otherwise you know we can
solve the we always have to solve the
kind of all kind of a possible SE and
then now from here to here
we can actually using our sum
rule so please look at this one
s2t oh this summation of
s2t now we can use a sum rule right we
can actually marginalize out
everything so now uh this is the
result so there's no summation over the
sequence right uh and then only have a
kind of the this the pi S1 and the PS1
or given Ceta by the way how to the
solve this one is actually in the next
week so this is actually not easy but we
can still make it so but yeah luckily we
can actually solve this one without
considering the all possible the
summation so this is actually the the
one reason that the EM algorithm hmm is
used if we have other kind of a
conditions and so on actually we
couldn't find this kind of a property
and then we couldn't avoid the summation
over the sequence but this kind of hmm
and EM em algorithm combination
magically mirac luckily we can find this
kind of a
solution okay so the this is just for
the uh one of the
part uh of this kind of the aary
function so let's go through the same
kind of formulation to the all other
part and the next the target is
transition weight and this one is again
uh we just using the
uh technique that I mentioned to solve
this kind of a problem protol so we
actually using the exactly same
technique sequence decomposition to the
the just rewriting the SE the 1 to T
minus 2 is tus One S and the subse of
tus one plus and then after that we
actually using the uh the distributed
property and then this log part is
moving here and then now let's cook this
one and actually we can use the sum rule
to marginalize the order kind of
variable and then uh look at this one
there's no summation over the sequence
right yeah the I was very impressed but
some of you maybe just kind of the
trival but I was very impressed by this
equation yeah and we can do the same
things uh for the uh the uh uh
gaussian uh the part uh and so on and I
just skipping the kind of a uh the
derivation and skipping means probably
this is the homework I don't remember
but probably that is the homework yeah
but by the way this one also this part
is know we are familiar but this part is
still not familiar we don't know how to
kind of obtain it again that part I will
explain it in the next week and the same
for the state transition uh this part is
I already explained you know we just
using Mar nomial distribution based on
the state transition but this part I
didn't explain it and this will be
explained in next
week so this is actually summary of the
auxiliary
function so initially this one is the
summation over the sequence which we
cannot
solve the but if we have you know 10 to
the the power of 92 or something like
that of the memory we can solve this but
otherwise we can solve it but by using
this other the equ
the the auxilary function we could
actually remove all the kind of
summation over the sequence and then
make that this kind of computation
tractable very cool uh however I didn't
mention about you know how to kind of
solve this part so that I will explain
in the later in the quad B
algorithm and the last part is a
parameter estimation
actually given this kind of a the form
we could actually easily estimate the
solution of the
parameter so uh what we will do is
actually the the directory getting the
derivative and and and then equal zero
to get the kind of all the kind of the
pi uh the A muj and RJ which is a kind
of our parameters in our problem that
can be actually solved by the uh the
this the the parameter estimation method
and so on by the way I think I didn't
mention uh I use the diagonal Coan
gaussian with a vector form which is a
little bit different from other people's
notation so please make sure this one is
you know the
vector calan Matrix should be Matrix uh
yes I know but this this is my
definition and this means that Vector
each Vector correspond to the diagonal
component and there is the actually
definition in the previous my slide and
so on so please do not confuse and so on
uh by the way how to solve it and how to
derive these Solutions are are the one
of the
homework so this the this week the the
weekly assignment is a little bit kind
of difficult but I hope you guys
can understand it by the way when
solving this one maybe I can explain
later in the weekly assignment uh so I I
will skip it okay so uh I can finish it
the uh uh we will still have to explain
the weekly assignment so the the we for
while it's until 50 right yeah we still
have more than 10 minutes so I can
explain it so now the I use kind of a
bit M and then the uh the the uh the uh
the the F kind of uh the make the kind
of speech problem to be the tractable
based on the EM algorithm and I
explained the this kind of four step the
introduction of the latent variable
complete dat likelihood auxiliary
function which I spend probably more the
longest the since you know summation
over sequence is kind of quite uh
difficult uh which is kind of elegantly
actually avoided in this formulation and
then parameter estimation but I quickly
mention it but it can be actually one of
the homework uh however I still didn't
touch for example uh the some of the uh
the uh the uh the variable that
introduced theing the Eep which I will
explain it in the next week by the way
we also have to sometimes get comput
this
value and here we also have a Commission
of sequence and we will also have to
avoid it that we will also explain next
week but basically uh please remember
that once this guys appeared we should
be very careful about it